Today I have just one request.
اليوم لدي طلب واحد منك.
Please don't tell me I'm normal.
من فضلك لا تخبرني باني طبيعية.
Now I'd like to introduce you to my brothers.
الان اريد ان اعرفك على اخواني.
Remi is 22,
ريمي في ال 22 من العمر
tall and very handsome.
طويل ووسيم جداً
He's speechless, but he communicates joy
هو ابكم, لكنه ينشر السعادة
in a way that some of the best orators cannot.
بطريقة لا يجاريه فيها بعض من افضل الخطباء.
Remi knows what love is.
ريمي يعلم ما هو الحب.
He shares it unconditionally and he shares it regardless.
ينشره بلا شروط و ينشره بلا حدود.
He's not greedy. He doesn't see skin color.
هو ليس جشعاً.هو لا يعتبر للأختلافات في لون البشرة.
He doesn't care about religious differences, and get this:
هو لا يهتم للاختلافات الدينية , وخذ هذه:
He has never told a lie.
لم يكذب ابداَ.
When he sings songs from our childhood,
عندما يغني اغنية من زمن الطفولة
attempting words that not even I could remember,
يسترجع كلمات لا استطيع حتى تذكرها
he reminds me of one thing:
هو ينبهني لشيئ واحد:
how little we know about the mind, and how wonderful
كم هو قليل ما نعلمه عن العقل وكم هو مبهر
the unknown must be.
الذي لا نعلمه عنه.
Samuel is 16. He's tall. He's very handsome.
صامويل هو في ال16 من العمر.طويل ووسيم جداً.
He has the most impeccable memory.
له ذاكرة مبهرة لا تشوبها شائبة.
He has a selective one, though.
مع ذلك ، ذاكرته إنتقائية.
He doesn't remember if he stole my chocolate bar,
هو لا يتذكر لو انه سرق مني لوح الشوكلا،
but he remembers the year of release for every song on my iPod,
لكنه يتذكر السنة التي انتجت فيها اي من الاغاني على الايبود خاصتي
conversations we had when he was four,
والمحادثات التي اجريناها عندما كان في الرابعة
weeing on my arm on the first ever episode of Teletubbies,
والتبول على ذراعي في اول حلقة من تلاتبيس
and Lady Gaga's birthday.
و عيد ميلاد ليدي غاغا.
Don't they sound incredible?
أليسوا رائعين؟
But most people don't agree.
لكن معظم الناس لا يوافقونني الرأي
And in fact, because their minds don't fit
ونسبة لأن عقولهم ليست موافقة
into society's version of normal,
لرؤية المجتمع عن العقول "الطبيعية"
they're often bypassed and misunderstood.
فانهم غالبا ما يُتجاهلوا ويساء فهمهم.
But what lifted my heart and strengthened my soul
لكن ما افرح فؤادي وقوى روحي
was that even though this was the case,
هو انه ومع انه هذا هو الواقع
although they were not seen as ordinary,
وبالرغم من انهم لا ينظر اليهم كمألوفين
this could only mean one thing:
فانه يعني شيئ واحد فقط
that they were extraordinary --
انهم استثنائيون
autistic and extraordinary.
متوحدون واستثنائيون.
Now, for you who may be less familiar with the term "autism,"
الان, وللذين لا يعلمون ما هو "التوحد"
it's a complex brain disorder that affects social communication,
فهو عبارة عن خلل دماغي معقد يؤثر على التواصل الاجتماعي
learning and sometimes physical skills.
والتعلم واحيانا المهارات البدنية.
It manifests in each individual differently,
التوحد يظهر في كل شخص بشكل مختلف عن الاخر
hence why Remi is so different from Sam.
لذلك ريمى مختلف جدا عن صامويل.
And across the world, every 20 minutes, one new person
وعبر العالم, كل 20 دقيقة يوجد شخص جديد
is diagnosed with autism, and although it's one of
تشخص حالته على انها توحد وبالرغم من انه
the fastest-growing developmental disorders in the world,
اسرع الاضرابات نموا في العالم
there is no known cause or cure.
لا يوجد له مسبب او علاج.
And I cannot remember the first moment I encountered autism,
لا استطيع تذكر اللحظة التي عرفت فيها التوحد لاول مرة
but I cannot recall a day without it.
لكني لا اذكر يوما دونه .
I was just three years old when my brother came along,
لقد كان عمري 3 سنين فقط عندما ولد اخي
and I was so excited that
وكنت متحمسة جدا
I had a new being in my life.
لقد قدم كائن جديد لحياتي !
And after a few months went by,
وبعد اشهر قليلة مرت
I realized that he was different.
أدركت انه مختلف.
He screamed a lot.
كان يصرخ كثيرا.
He didn't want to play like the other babies did,
لم يرد اللعب مثل باقي الاطفال.
and in fact, he didn't seem
وحقيقة لم يبدو
very interested in me whatsoever.
مهتم بي اطلاقا.
Remi lived and reigned in his own world, with his own rules,
ريمى عاش وأدار عالمه الخاص وبقوانينه الخاصة،
and he found pleasure in the smallest things,
لقد وجد متعة في الاشياء الصغيرة،
like lining up cars around the room
كاصطفاف السيارات في جميع انحاء الغرفة
and staring at the washing machine
و التحديق في الة الغسيل
and eating anything that came in between.
و اكل أي شيئ استطاع الوصول اليه.
And as he grew older, he grew more different,
وعندما كبر قليلا اصبح اكثر اختلافا
and the differences became more obvious.
واصبحت الاختلافات اكثر وضوحا.
Yet beyond the tantrums and the frustration
لكن ومع نوبات الغضب والاحباط
and the never-ending hyperactivity
وفرط النشاط اللامنتهي
was something really unique:
كان هنالك شيئ فريد:
a pure and innocent nature, a boy who saw the world
طبيعة نقية وبريئة، طفل رأى العالم
without prejudice, a human who had never lied.
من غير تحيز,انسان لم يكذب ابدا.
Extraordinary.
انسان استثنائي.
Now, I cannot deny that there have been
الان,لا استطيع الانكار بأن هنالك
some challenging moments in my family,
بعض التحديات التي واجهت اسرتي،
moments where I've wished that they were just like me.
لحظات أملت فيها لو أنهم مثلي.
But I cast my mind back to the things that they've taught me
لكني صببت تفكيري في استرجاع الاشياء التي تعلمتها
about individuality and communication and love,
عن الشخصية والتواصل والحب
and I realize that these are things that
وادركت عندها ان هذه هي الاشياء
I wouldn't want to change with normality.
التي لا اريد ان تتغير مع "الطبيعية"
Normality overlooks the beauty that differences give us,
"الطبيعية" تؤثر سلباً على الجمال الذي تعطيه لنا الاختلافات
and the fact that we are different doesn't mean that one of us is wrong.
وحقيقة اننا مختلفون هذا لا يعني ابدا ان احدنا على خطأ.
It just means that there's a different kind of right.
انه فقط يعني ان هنالك اكثر من وجه للحقيقة.
And if I could communicate just one thing to Remi
واذا امكنني ان اوصل شيئ واحد لريمي
and to Sam
والى صامويل
and to you,
واليك انت
it would be that you don't have to be normal.
فهو انك لا يجب ان تصبح طبيعيا في حين انه
You can be extraordinary.
يمكنك ان تكون استثنائيا
Because autistic or not,
لانه سواء كنا متوحدون او لا
the differences that we have --
الاختلافات التي نحملها
We've got a gift! Everyone's got a gift inside of us,
هى عبارة عن هدية..اي واحد منا يمتلك شيئ مميزا داخله
and in all honesty, the pursuit of normality
وبكل صدق البحث عن "الطبيعية"
is the ultimate sacrifice of potential.
هي عبارة عن اهدار كبير للامكانيات
The chance for greatness, for progress and for change
الفرصة للعظمة والتقدم وللتغيير
dies the moment we try to be like someone else.
تموت في تلك اللحظة التي نسعى فيها لنكون نسخة ثانية من شخص ما
Please -- don't tell me I'm normal.
من فضلك--لا تقل لي انا طبيعية.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. .(تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)